<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A message from both Houses of Parliament sent to Yorke to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, the 28 of March 1642. With His Majesties letter to the Lord Keeper, in answer to the same, dated March the last, 1642.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1653A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221181</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52528812</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52528812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03011)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2770:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A message from both Houses of Parliament sent to Yorke to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, the 28 of March 1642. With His Majesties letter to the Lord Keeper, in answer to the same, dated March the last, 1642.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 4, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Andrew Coe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print dated: Sabbati 2. of April, 1642. Signed: Iohn Browne, Cler. Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Relates to the appointment of a commander for the English Navy, the Parliament recommending the Earl of Warwick for the post, the king replying that Sir John Pennington had been appointed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy --  Officers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Naval operations --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <p>A MESSAGE FROM BOTH HOVSES OF Parliament Sent to YORKE to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, the 28. of March 1642.</p>
            <p>With his Majeſties Letter to the Lord Keeper, in anſwer to the ſame, Dated March the laſt. 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Sabbati 2. of April, 1642.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Ordered by the Lords in Parliament, that the Meſſage of both Houſes to his Majeſty, dated 28. of March, 1642. That the Earle of Warwicke might command this Summers Fleet, in chiefe under the Lord Admirall: and his Majeſties Anſwer thereunto ſhall be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iohn Browne, Cler.Parliament.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Andrew Coe.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:178782:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178782:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, having found it neceſſary to provide, and ſet to Sea a ſtrong and powerfull Navy for the defence of this Kingdom againſt forrain force &amp; the ſecurity of your other dominions, the charge whereof is to be borne by the Common-wealth, and taking notice of the indiſpoſition of the Lord Admirall, which diſables him at this time for commanding the fleet in his owne perſon, did thereupon recommend unto his Lordſhip, the Earle of Warwicke (a perſon of ſuch quality and ability as in whom they might beſt confide) to ſupply his Lordſhips roome for this imployment, and underſtanding that your Majeſty hath ſince ſignified your pleaſure concerning that command to Sir <hi>Iohn Pennington,</hi> wee doe hold it our duty
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178782:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
to repreſent unto your Majeſty, the great danger and miſchiefe the Common-wealth is like to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine by ſuch interruption.</p>
            <p>And therefore doe humbly beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty that the perſon recommended by both Houſes of Parliament for this ſervice, may no longer bee detained from it out of any particular reſpect to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other perſon whatſoever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:178782:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <head>To our Right truſty and welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Counſellor, <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton,</hi> Keeper of our Great Sea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight truſty and welbeloved Counſellour, we greet you well:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>we wonder both at the forme and matter of that incloſed Paper ye ſent Us, (in the name of both Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in yours of the 28. of March) it beng neither by way of Petition, Declaration, or Leter, and for the matter, Wee beleeve it is the firſt ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that the houſes of Parliament have taken upon them the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or recommendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the chiefſea Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander; but it ads to the wonder, that Sir <hi>Iohn Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington</hi> being already appointed by Us for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, upon the recommendation of our Admirall, (which is ſo well known that none can be ignorant of it) and no fault ſo much as alledged againſt him, another ſhould be recommended to Us: Therefore Our Reſolution upon this poynt is, that Wee will not alter him, whom we have already appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178782:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
to command this yeares Fleet, whoſe every way ſuffeciency is ſo univerſally knowne, the which We are confident Our Admirall (if there ſhall bee occaſion) will make moſt evident (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whoſe Teſtimony We ſuppoſe our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not except) and though there were yet none appointed; or the ſaid Sir John (through ſome accident) not able to perform the ſervice, yet the men of that Profeſſion, are ſo well knowne to Us, (beſides many other Reaſons) that (our Admirall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccepted becauſe of his place) Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of that kind, would not be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Yorke,</hi> 
                  <date>the laſt of <hi>March,</hi> 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:178782:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:178782:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
